(
"ai_sub_version": "1.9.1",
"subtitles_prompt_version": 2,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": "gemini-cli:gemini-3-flash-preview",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"gemini_cli": (
"timeout": 600
)
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": true,
"fps": 1,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"encoder": "libx264"
)
),
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"subtitles": 8
),
"retry": (
"run": 3,
"max": 9,
"delay": 30
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": false,
"scrub": true
)
しくじりかなたそ　僕みたいになるな！！
Shikujiri Kanata-so: Don't become like me!!
（歓声）
(Cheers)
はい！ということで、こんかなた！今回教師を務める天音かなたです。よろしくお願いします。
Hi! So, Kon-Kanata! I'm Amane Kanata, serving as your teacher today. Nice to meet you.
よろしくお願いします。
Nice to meet you.
それでは生徒の皆さんの自己紹介を。
Now, students, please introduce yourselves.
はーい！もぐもぐ〜おかゆ！ホロライブゲーマーズの猫又おかゆです。よろしくお願いします、先生！
Hi! Mogu-mogu... Okayu! I'm Nekomata Okayu from Hololive Gamers. Looking forward to the class, Teacher!
はーい！ホロライブ５期生の顔が肝臓、雪花ラミィです。天音先生、よろしくお願いします！
Hi! I'm Yukihana Lamy from Hololive 5th Gen, with a face that's basically a liver. Nice to meet you, Amane-sensei!
はーい！先生！可愛いポジティブジーニアス！ホロライブデバイスのしくじり担当？一条莉々華です！
Hi! Teacher! Cute, positive, genius! In charge of "shikujiri" in Hololive DEV_IS? I'm Ichijou Ririka!
そんなことない大丈夫大丈夫。そんなことない全然。本当に皆さんお忙しい中集まっていただきありがとうございます。
That's not true, you're fine, you're fine. Not at all. Truly, thank you all for gathering here despite your busy schedules.
いえいえ、こちらこそ！楽しみ！
No, no, thank you! Looking forward to it!
あの、カニ奢りますから。
Um, I'll treat you all to crab later.
やったー！嬉しい！
Yay! So happy!
カニを持ってね、あのお礼とさせていただきますので。
I'll use crab as a token of my gratitude.
ということでね、今日はですね、本当にもう、天音かなた、僕がしくじってしまったやってしまった過去のしくじりをたくさん話して、
So, today, I, Amane Kanata, am going to talk a lot about my past failures and blunders,
みんな同じことを繰り返さないようにと、これからの活動の参考にしてもらえたらというようなものでして。
so that you don't repeat the same mistakes, and can use this as a reference for your future activities.
じゃあちょっと早速なんですが、僕のしくじりについて授業を始めていきたいと思います！
Now, without further ado, let's start the lesson about my failures!
それではですね、皆さんお手元にあります教科書の１ページ目を開いてください。
Now, please open the first page of the textbook in front of you.
はーい。
Yes.
授業テーマ「デビュー直後のキャラ迷走！天音かなたのしくじり人生！」
Lesson Theme: "Character Identity Crisis Right After Debut! Amane Kanata's Life of Failures!"
おおー。なるほど。
Ohh. I see.
え、でもそんなことあったっけ？
Wait, did that actually happen?
あったんですね、実は。
It actually did, believe it or not.
じゃあまずはデビュー直後の天音かなたのホロライブ人生の上がり下がりをグラフにしてみました。次のページ！
First, I've made a graph showing the ups and downs of my life in Hololive right after debut. Next page!
下がってるね！こんなに！えー！？
It's crashing! This much!? What!?
そうですね、やっぱりデビューが100だとしたら、だんだんだんだん下がっていって、50%。まだ１年も経たないうちに、もう20%とかその辺に。
Right, if the debut was at 100, it gradually went down to 50%. And within less than a year, it was already around 20% or so.
急降下しましたね。
It took a nosedive, didn't it?
すご。そんな、何があったんですか？
Wow. What happened to make that happen?
いや、ちょっと、何があったのか
Well, I'm going to...
解説していきたいと思います。
...explain exactly what happened.
はい！
Yes!
僕は2019年12月27日、
I debuted on December 27, 2019,
約5年前ですね。デビューしたんですけど、
about five years ago now.
うん。
Mm-hmm.
デビュー前、「これから...
Before my debut, I thought...
楽しいホロライブ人生が始まるんだ！」
"a fun Hololive life is about to begin!"
と、期待に胸を大きく膨らませていました。
And I was filled with great anticipation.
なんて？なんて？
What? What's that?
そんな平らなのに？
Even though it's that flat?
ちょっと！
Wait a minute!
やばいやばいやばい！
Oh no, oh no, oh no!
あれですよね。膨らみすぎて、
Oh, I see. It expanded so much...
破裂しちゃっただけですもんね。
...that it just burst, right?
破裂しかけて、
It was about to burst...
まだ膨らみ続けているという感じなんですが。
...and is still expanding.
デビュー前はね、あの、
Before my debut,
憧れの先輩たち一人ひとりに、
I contacted each of the seniors I admired...
全部違う文章で連絡をしました。
...with a different message for everyone.
くれてた、くれてた！
You did, you did!
おかゆちゃんにも送りましたし、
I sent one to Okayu-chan too.
頑張ってデビュー配信の資料を作ったり
I also worked hard on the materials...
もしてて。
...for my debut stream.
資料？
Materials?
そうなんですよ。
That's right.
みんなデビュー前ってどんな感じでした？
What was it like for everyone else before debut?
え、莉々華ほんとまだ直近じゃないですか？
Well, I just debuted recently.
そうだね。
True.
確かに。
Indeed.
偉大なる先輩たちの配信をいっぱい見て研究して、
I watched and researched many streams by my great seniors,
3か月〜4か月かけて、
and spent three or four months...
デビュー配信の準備しました。
...preparing for my debut stream.
すごい！本格的！
Amazing! So professional!
ラミィもデビューするまでは
I also spent months...
何か月もかけてデビュー初配信の準備してた。
...preparing for my first debut stream.
おかゆんは？
What about Okayun?
僕の時は、その、準備とかないから。
In my case, there wasn't really much preparation.
えええー！
Whaaat?!
全然もう。
Not at all.
1時間もたせるために、ちょっとした工夫はありましたけど、
I did some small things to make it last an hour,
今の子たちの初配信とは
but compared to the debut streams today,
クオリティの差がハンパなかったですよ。
the difference in quality was huge.
そうなんだ。
Is that so?
確かにどんどんね、やっぱり、
It's true that gradually,
初配信ってクオリティが上がっていって、
the quality of debut streams has gone up.
いきなりオリ曲があるとか、
Like having an original song right away,
オープニングにアニメーションがあるとか、
or an animated opening sequence.
あったと思うんですけど、
I've seen those kinds of things.
その大事な初配信では、
But in that important first stream,
こんなしくじりをしました。
I made this mistake.
次のページ。
Next page.
天音かなたのデビュー配信
Amane Kanata's Debut Stream
パワーポイントで自分を紹介
Introducing herself with PowerPoint
視聴者の意見
Viewer's Opinion
クッソダサい
Ugly/Tacky as hell
あった、あった〜！
Oh, I remember that!
一生懸命、
I worked so hard...
1か月以上かけて作ったパワーポイントの資料が、
...spending over a month on my PowerPoint materials,
酷評されてしまいました。
...only for them to be panned.
あの、そんな僕の初配信の映像がございますので、
Well, I have footage from my first stream,
見てほしいんです。
so I want you to see it.
映像がこちら！
Here's the video!
ジャン！
Ta-da!
ダサ、ダサ！
So tacky!
ようこそ
Welcome
何？今のクッソダサいの何？
What? What was that tacky thing?
ダサい！
Tacky!
★天音かなたの初配信へ★
★To Amane Kanata's first stream★
アニメーションできてきた！
Here comes the animation!
星マークえぐ！
That star symbol is crazy!
自己紹介
Self-Introduction
謎の寿司！
Mysterious sushi!
なんだこの寿司？
What's with the sushi?
解像度高いな、やけに。
The resolution is strangely high.
自己紹介していきたいと思います。
I'd like to introduce myself.
美味しそう。
Looks delicious.
【名前】天音かなた
[Name] Amane Kanata
うわ、下からブワーってきた！
Whoa, it popped up from below!
読みにくっ！
So hard to read!
天音かなたと申します。
My name is Amane Kanata.
夢や目標
Dreams and Goals
クルクルしてる、じゃん。
Wait, it's spinning.
ニコニコマークも出してきた。
She brought out a smiley face too.
②登録者数5万人！！
2. 50,000 subscribers!!
これをね、皆さんホロライブ好きな方分かると思うんですけど、
I think those of you who like Hololive will understand,
まず、3D化したい！
but first, I want to get a 3D model!
ってことで5万人まず目指そうってとこですね。
So my first goal is 50,000 subscribers.
ライブに出演してコールアンドレスポンスをやりたい。
I want to perform at a concert and do call-and-response.
あれね、ちょっとね、夢ですね。
That's, well, it's a dream of mine.
今のパワーポイントの準備に、
Preparing that PowerPoint...
1か月ガチでかけてます。
...actually took me a whole month.
ヤバすぎる！
That's crazy!
すごい言われましたね、同期にも。
My gen-mates really gave me a hard time about it.
「その1か月他のことできただろう」とか。
"You could've done so many other things in that month."
色々言われたんですけど、皆さんどうでしたか？
They said a lot, but what did you all think?
おしゃれでした？
Was it stylish?
正直に、莉々華どうだった？
Honestly, Ririka, what did you think?
クッソダサいです！
It's tacky as hell!
すいません、先生！
Sorry, Sensei!
うわあああ！
Noooo!
やっぱダサい？
Is it really tacky?
うん。
Yeah.
それがかなたんの良さだよね。
But that's what's good about Kanatan.
ちょっとダサい。
A little tacky.
個性はあったよね。
It definitely had personality.
PP天使とか言われてたしね。
You were even called "PP Angel" because of it.
未だに海外ニキはPPエンジェルって言ってくれる。
Overseas fans still call me "PP Angel."
Tシャツもありますもんね。
There's even a T-shirt for it.
最初に出したやつね、水色のね。
The first one I released, the light blue one.
そうなんですよ。
That's right.
しかもデビュー配信では他にも、
And that's not all for my debut stream.
全部自分の声で演奏から作った
I played a 'Soran Bushi'...
ソーラン節を流したり、
...that I made entirely with my own voice.
尖ったデビュー配信をせねばとやっておりましたが。
I felt I had to do an edgy debut stream.
ソーラン節ってなんですか？
What's the 'Soran Bushi'?
ソーラン節ね。
The 'Soran Bushi'...
見たいですか？
Do you want to see it?
見たい！
We want to see it!
映像があるのでご覧ください。
I have the video, so please take a look.
ソーラン節
Soran Bushi
ドッコイショドッコイショ！
Heave-ho, heave-ho!
いらすとやさんも使用してます。
She's using Irasutoya assets too.
そうだね。
That's right.
ちゃんとコールも黄色くなってて。
The calls are even highlighted in yellow.
みんなが言うとこもあるんだ。
There's a part for the audience to join in.
おい、すごい。
Wow, that's amazing.
低音も高音も聞こえる。
I can hear both low and high notes.
いっぱいいる。
There are so many voices.
ドッコイショ！ドッコイショ！
Heave-ho! Heave-ho!
始まった、始まった！
It started, it started!
エコーかかってる。
There's an echo.
ちょっとね、まだ慣れてないボフボフのエコーかかってます。
Yeah, it's a bit of a muffled echo from before I was used to it.
一応、右上を見ていただくと、
If you look at the top right,
みんな「ドッコイショ」って一応言ってくれてる。
everyone is actually saying "Heave-ho."
本当だ。本当だね。
You're right. They really are.
これ最後のドヤ顔ね。
And this is the final smug face.
これ何？
What is this?
やかんやん。
It's like a kettle.
やかん。
A kettle.
こんな配信をしてますが、
Despite streaming like this,
実は初めはクールキャラでいこうと考えてて。
I actually planned to go with a "cool character" at first.
それでっ！
And so!
やっぱり参考にしていたのはおかゆ先輩...
As I thought, the one I used as a reference
was Okayu-senpai...
わぁ〜
Wow~
これはもう本当に間違いがなくね...
There's no mistake about that...
いや〜ありがたいね、ね？
Man, I'm honored. Right?
まぁクールぶっていたけど、なんかダサいらしいパワーポイントを駆使して
I was acting cool, but while using what was
apparently tacky PowerPoints...
今後の迷走を予感させる配信となってしまいました。
...it became a stream that foreshadowed
my future identity crisis.
でもみんなも初配信はあるということで、皆さんどうですか？
But since everyone has a debut stream,
how about you guys?
自分の初配信覚えてますか？おかゆ先輩！
Do you remember your own debut stream,
Okayu-senpai?
覚えてますよ。
I remember it.
まぁ若かった。
Well, I was young.
今も若いですよ！
You're still young now!
もう7年目かな？
Is it my 7th year already?
7年の経過と思うと、それは確かに時間が経って大人になっているか...
Thinking about the passage of 7 years,
you've definitely grown up...
それは感じるかな。
I do feel that.
そう、デビュー配信も僕も終わり、ダサいと言われつつも、1週間後に先程夢で掲げました登録者5万人を達成し、
Right. My debut stream ended, and despite
being called tacky, a week later I reached
1週間後に先程夢で掲げました登録者5万人を達成し、
the 50,000 subscribers I mentioned dreaming
of earlier.
出だしは非常に順調だったんですが...
The start was extremely smooth, but...
僕はこういう気持ちを抱くようになります。次のページ。
I started to feel this way. Next page.
プレッシャーだな
What pressure...
わかる〜
I get it~
やっぱりホロライブというところに所属させていただいたことによる、リスナーさん数字とかってあったので、
After all, belonging to Hololive brought expectations
regarding viewers and numbers.
特にそのデビューして何もしてないから、いいのかな？これでっていうのを感じたりしましたね。
Since I'd just debuted and hadn't done anything,
I wondered if it was really okay like this.
皆さんはこうデビューしたての時ってどうでしたか？
What was it like for you all when you first debuted?
ラミィはもうそれこそ4期生が盛り上がってるところでデビューしたので、
For me, I debuted right when the 4th generation
was reaching peak excitement,
プレッシャーもすごかったし、結構批判的な意見も多かった。
so the pressure was immense, and there
were many critical opinions.
え〜、どんな？
Oh, like what?
いやもう、あの...ゴキブリの5期生とか...
Well, things like... "Cockroaches of the 5th gen"...
ええ〜〜！！
Ehh~~!!
ひどいよ！
That's terrible!
「才能なし」みたいな。
Things like "no talent."
すごい言われましたよ。
I was told that a lot.
でもやっぱりこう先輩が築き上げてきたものに乗っかってる感じだったので...
But I felt like I was just riding on the success
that our seniors had built up...
気持ちはわかる。
I know the feeling.
プレッシャーがすごかった。
The pressure was incredible.
おかゆ先輩あった？プレッシャー。
Did you have pressure, Okayu-senpai?
いや僕が入った時はもうそんなね、まだまだ人も少なくて、
No, when I joined, there weren't that many people yet,
大空スバル選手権の前日に大空スバルのモノマネの練習をするだけで1時間枠取ったりしてたから...
so I'd do an hour-long stream just practicing
Subaru impressions the day before the Subaru Championship...
プレッシャー感じなくていいからマジで！
You seriously don't need to feel pressure!
古き良きホロライブを感じますね。
I feel the good old days of Hololive.
そんなこともありましたよ。
Things like that happened too.
僕もやっぱりデビュー直後だったので、特に先輩たちにも恩返ししたいとかリスナーさんにも何かとか、
I was also right after my debut, so I was thinking
a lot about giving back to my seniors and fans.
そういうことをすごく考えていました。
I was constantly thinking about those things.
そしてこの考えが悪い方に働いてしまい、その結果僕はこうなってしまいます。次のページ。
And this mindset ended up backfiring,
leading to this. Next page.
暗黒の初期かなた時代
The Dark Age of early Kanata
暗黒ですか。
A Dark Age?
暗黒...
Dark...
もうとんでもない暗黒の時代でした。
It was an absolute Dark Age.
初期かなたがどんな感じだったのか、デビュー当時の状況を説明しますと、
To explain what early Kanata was like,
here's the situation at the time of my debut.
当時はARKというゲームが大流行しておりまして、
At the time, the game ARK was incredibly popular,
流行ってた！流行ってた！
It was! Everyone was playing it!
みんなやってたもんね。
Everyone was playing it back then.
僕はゲームに慣れてなかったんで、ゲームもワタワタしつつコラボもしつつ、
I wasn't used to gaming, so I was flustered
while playing and collaborating,
喋りもいっぱい頑張って、でもコメントも拾わなきゃと全部やろうとしたら...
and trying to talk and read comments all at once.
When I tried to do everything...
先輩が喋ってるのにコメントを読んだりとか、空気が読めていない「初期かなた」誕生と。
...I'd read comments while my seniors were
talking. Thus, the socially awkward "Early Kanata"
was born.
ああ...
Ah...
焦りから異常に空気が読めてないのに無駄に積極的に話しかけてくる、
Unable to read the room due to nerves,
yet aggressively trying to talk to everyone,
だる絡みの初期かなた。
it was the annoying early Kanata.
これね、結構見てたんだけど、ちょっと苦しくなる。
I watched quite a bit of that,
but it's actually painful to see.
胸がキュッてなる。
It makes my heart sink.
共感性羞恥と、あぁこの子っていう。
It's a mix of secondhand embarrassment
and feeling bad for her.
その悪意がないのは多分伝わるので、キュッとなる系ではありますね。
Since there's no malice, it's just painful
to watch her try so hard.
頑張ろうとしてた感じが。
Like, she was trying her best.
おかゆ先輩、初期かなた時代の僕って覚えてますか？
Okayu-senpai, do you remember me from
my early days?
いや僕実は、ARKって1回ぐらいしか参加してないから。
Actually, I only participated in ARK about once.
だから配信中のかなたんより、配信してないかなたんと関わる方が多かったんです。
So I actually spent more time with you
off-stream than watching your streams.
配信してないかなたんは今とあんまり変わんないと思う。
Off-stream Kanatan was pretty much the same
as you are now.
そうなんです。実は配信外では普通だったので。
Exactly. I was actually normal off-stream.
なんで配信中はこんなおかしくて、裏では普通に話せるのに
The other Holo-members even asked me,
"Why are you so weird on stream
「あんたなんでなの？」っていうのをホロメンに言われたこともありました。
when you're so normal in person?"
初期かなたを見たリスナーの反応はと言うと、次のページ。
As for the listeners' reactions to early Kanata...
Next page.
「推しに絡まないで欲しい！」「早く辞めろ」
"Don't get involved with my oshi!"
"Quit already!"
もちろん応援してくれる人もたくさんいたんですけど、
Of course, there were plenty of people
supporting me too, but...
実はこれ、配信開始をする前、待機所の状態でコメントが大荒れしたこともあって...
Actually, even before the stream started,
the waiting room chat would be in an uproar...
500人ぐらいの人がず〜っと言い合いをする
Around 500 people were constantly arguing...
こともあるほど、やっぱりリスナーさんからちょっと嫌われてる時期がありましたね。
...to the point where there was a period when I was somewhat disliked by the listeners.
あ〜、そうなんだ。
Oh, I see.
今じゃ考えられないけど。
It's hard to imagine that now.
いやいや、そんなことないんですけど、これ具体的にね、どんな感じだったかと言いますと...
No, no, but let me tell you specifically what it was like...
怖い
Scary.
・コラボの流れをぶった斬ってコメント読み
• Interrupting the flow of a collab to read comments.
・面白いことを言おうとして空回り
• Trying too hard to be funny and failing miserably.
・コラボ相手のオウム返し
• Parrot-like repetition of collab partners' words.
ということが、結構多かった。
Things like that happened quite a bit.
まあオウム返しも焦りから何か言わなきゃ、
The parroting was probably because I felt like I had to say something,
沈黙を作らないようにっていうのが多分焦りすぎて
trying so hard not to let any silence occur...
悪循環になってしまったということがありましたね。
that I just ended up in a vicious cycle.
これはもう初期かなた、本当に大きなしくじりなんですが、
That was a really big blunder in my early days...
みんなは新人時代の自分を振り返ってみてどうですか？ありますか？
How about you guys, looking back at your rookie days? Anything like that?
ううっ...
Ugh...
震えてる。
She's shaking.
初期ラミィをいじられるほど、初期とキャラが変わってるので、
Lamy's character has changed so much since the early days...
ちょっと昔のラミィを思い出すだけで「ううっ」ってなるんですけど。
...that just remembering her old self makes her go 'ugh'.
やっぱこう求められる像にならなきゃみたいな、
I felt like I had to become the image expected of me.
リスナーさんがこんなラミィを求めてるだろうみたいなのに
I tried to meet what I thought the listeners wanted from Lamy,
応えようとしてああなっていったみたいな。
and that's how I ended up like that.
「ホロライブは清楚を求めている」みたいなね。
Like, 'Hololive expects us to be pure'.
莉々華はちょっと前のことだけど、変わったって思うことある？
Ririka, it wasn't that long ago for you, but do you feel you've changed?
いや、もう莉々華いまも現在進行系で、
No, I'm still dealing with exactly those things right now.
いまお話されてたみたいなことに悩まされてて、
I'm struggling with the same problems you mentioned...
もう今帰りたーいです。帰りたい。
...I just want to go home right now. I want to go home.
ダメだよ！ダメダメダメダメ！
No! No, no, no, no!
いやでもやっぱ一皮剥けたい！頑張りたいです！
But I really want to break out of my shell! I want to do my best!
莉々華、めちゃめちゃいいと思いますよ、大丈夫だよ。
Ririka, I think you're doing great, it's okay.
まあこんな感じでね、良かれと思って、
So, like this, even though I'm an introvert at heart,
根は陰キャなのに頑張って先輩たちに話し掛けまくって、
I tried too hard to talk to my seniors,
空回りする僕は、自分の精神、
and ended up just spinning my wheels. The gap...
素の性格とキャラのズレが大きくなっていきます。
...between my true personality and my character kept growing.
そして自分が表でやっていく上でのキャラクターを
And then, I had to course-correct to a character...
自分の性格に合ったキャラクターに軌道修正することになります。
...that actually fits my true personality for my public presence.
「はっちゃけキャラやめよう」と。
I decided to stop trying to be the high-energy character.
結局ね、やっぱりキャラに無理があると精神が削られるんですよね？
After all, if you're forcing a character, it wears you down mentally, right?
ね？ね？
Right? Right?
分かります！！！
I understand!!!
とっても分かります！
I understand completely!
ちなみにホロメンとうまく絡めなかったとか配信後に後悔した経験がある人いますか？
By the way, has anyone ever regretted not interacting well with other members after a stream?
莉々華？
Ririka?
全然ないですけどね... なんかそんな...
Not at all... nothing like that...
お酒を飲んで、ね、すごい後悔して、
Well, I drank, you know, and I regretted it so much.
ラミィ先輩にあのDiscordで、あの、本当に申し訳ございませんでした。
I sent Lamy-senpai a message on Discord saying, 'I'm truly sorry.'
よろしければまた一緒に遊んでいただけると嬉しいさ、
'I'd be happy if we could hang out together again.'
つい、ついい昨日の話ですね。ついつい今年の話ですね。
Wait, that was just... that was just this year.
そんなこともあって、僕、一時期、気持ちがどん底まで落ち続けてしまいましたが、
Because of things like that, my mood hit rock bottom for a while,
迷走しながらも配信を頑張って続けることで、
but by pushing through and continuing my streams even while feeling lost,
プラスの影響が起きていきます。次のページ。
positive things started to happen. Next page!
配信を続ける中でキャラが定着
Character established while continuing streaming
ということでね、まあ長い時間をかけつつではありますが、
So, it took a long time, but through relationships built in streams...
配信の中でできた関係性やホロメンにいじってもらってね、
...and being teased by other members,
いい感じでキャラが定着したり、自分のことをみんなに知ってもらったりして、
my character settled into a good place and people got to know me,
配信がだんだんだんだんやりやすくなってきいきます。
and streaming gradually became easier and easier.
配信で定着した天音かなたのキャラがこちら、次のページ。
Here is the Amane Kanata character that became established. Next page.
・センスなしキャラ ・握力ゴリラキャラ ・ツッコミキャラ
• No-sense character
• Grip-strength gorilla character
• Tsukkomi character
まあセンスなしキャラについてはね、僕はちょっと認めてないんですけど。
Well, as for the 'no-sense' character, I don't really accept it.
認めてないんだ？
You don't?
周りからダサいと言われた代表的なものがたくさんあるんですよ。
There are many classic examples of people calling me uncool.
・PP天使
• PP Tenshi
・洋服がダサい
• Unfashionable clothes
・#かなたやめろ
• #KanataYamero (Stop it Kanata)
PP天使はさきほど紹介しましたが、僕のセンスなしキャラについて思い当たる節ありますか？
I already introduced PP Tenshi, but do you guys have any thoughts on my 'no-sense' character?
いやー... ないよね！？
No... we don't, right!?
いや、でもあるっちゃあるというか...
Well... but, I mean, there is something...
一時期、かなたんの洋服について話し合うDiscordのグループがあったりとかね。
For a while, there was actually a Discord group to discuss Kanatan's clothes.
ラミィとミオ先輩とマリンを集めて突然作って、
I suddenly gathered Lamy, Mio-senpai, and Marine and said...
「洋服がダサいって言われるんでおしゃれな洋服（ネットで買える）を教えてください」
'People say my clothes are uncool, so please teach me about stylish clothes I can buy online.'
外に買いに行かないんだ。
She won't go out to buy them.
ネットで買えるのが大事なんだ。
Being able to buy online is the key.
外には行きたくなかったっていう専用部屋であったりもしましたね。
That's true, it was a dedicated room because I didn't want to go outside.
さきほど「かなたやめろ」がトレンド入りしたって言ってたと思うんですけど何なんですか？
You mentioned earlier that '#KanataYamero' trended. What on earth was that?
これは僕のメンバーシップの名前を付ける時の話なんだけど、
That was when I was choosing a name for my membership.
名前の候補が3つありまして...
I originally had three candidates...
・かなたーず ・THEかなた ・かなたふぁんくらぶ
• Kanata-zu
• THE Kanata
• Kanata Fan Club
これはな〜、こちらどうですか？可愛いよね？
Look at these... what do you think? They're cute, right?
これは... まあ... うん... 可愛いよね？
These are... well... yeah... cute, right?
まあこんな感じで候補がありまして...
Well, there were these candidates...
はい、このリスナーさんのね、反応がこちら！
Yes, here are the reactions from the listeners!
全部ダサいってすごい
It's amazing how they're all tacky.
ここまで悩むアンケートは初めて
This is the first time I've ever struggled this much with a poll.
センスが息をしていない
Her sense of style is dead.
ボロクソやん！
They're trash-talking me!
厳しいなー
That's harsh.
悩んでアンケート入れられないと。
They can't even vote because they're struggling too much.
なるほどねー。
I see.
ネーミングセンスがダサすぎたということで、この時「#かなたやめろ」のハッシュタグがつけられ、
Because my naming sense was so tacky, the hashtag #KanataStopIt was used,
なんと日本のトレンドに入ります！
and it actually trended in Japan!
すごい！
Amazing!
だめだよと、恥ずかしいな。
No way, that's embarrassing.
おかしいでしょ。でもどの名前が良いかなって当時のね、Twitterで投票してもらったんですけど、その結果がこうなります。
That's weird. But I asked people on Twitter back then to vote for which name was best, and this was the result.
（ドラムロール）
(Drum roll)
「THEかなた」が選ばれたと。
"THE Kanata" was chosen.
おお、でもなんか全部ほぼ一緒で、みんな悩んでる。
Oh, but they're all almost the same, everyone's struggling.
ちょっとね、僅差なの。
It was a small difference.
大接戦の末、「THEかなた」に決定したんですよね。
After a close battle, it was decided on "THE Kanata."
悩んだだろうな、これみんな。
Everyone must have struggled with this.
そう、みんな悩みましたね。
Yeah, everyone struggled.
結局時を経て、去年あたりですかね、「THEかなた」がダサいことに私は気づきました。
Eventually, as time passed, maybe around last year, I realized that "THE Kanata" was tacky.
あ、気づきを得た！
Oh, she gained an insight!
なんか、いろんなみんながおしゃれな名前だったりとか、ストレートにファンネームをつけているみんなのメンバーシップを見て、
Looking at everyone's memberships with stylish names or simple fan names,
「あ、THEかなたってダサかったんだ」と思いまして、
I thought, "Oh, THE Kanata was tacky,"
現在のメンバーシップの名前は「へいみん」になっております。
and now my membership name is "Heimin."
よかった〜、そういうこと...
Thank goodness, so that's it...
拍手すんな、よかったじゃない！残念だろ。
Don't clap! It's not "thank goodness!" It's unfortunate.
え、でも他にもちょっとかなた先輩といえばで、気になってることがあって。
But there's something else about you, Kanata-senpai, that I'm curious about.
かなた先輩、握力キャラというか、力がめっちゃあるみたいな感じで、自己紹介とかでも言ってると思うんですけど、あれは最初からではなかったんですか？
You have this "grip strength" character, or like you're super strong, and I think you say it in your introductions, but was that not there from the start?
いや、そうだね。自己紹介で言うようになったのは途中からね。
No, that's right. I only started saying it in my introductions partway through.
昔から、本当に中学校とかの頃かな、握力が強くて。
Since long ago, maybe around middle school, I had strong grip strength.
雑談の中でね、握力50kgあったんだよねーみたいなこと言ったりとか、
I'd mention in streams like, "My grip strength was 50kg,"
もう力強くて物が壊れちゃうって話をよくしてたら、なんかだんだんだんだん、わかんないけど「握力ゴリラキャラ」が定着していって。
and if I often talked about being so strong I'd break things, then gradually, I don't know why, but the "Grip Strength Gorilla" character stuck.
そんな僕がね、今までうっかり握りつぶしたものは、こちらです。
Here are the things I've accidentally crushed.
お寿司、マカロン、蒸したジャガイモ、お弁当のスプーン、コーヒーメーカー、キーボード、Switchのコントローラーなどなどですね。
Sushi, macarons, steamed potatoes, lunchbox spoons, coffee makers, keyboards, Switch controllers, and so on.
多いなぁ。
That's a lot.
まあお寿司とかマカロンは、マカロン初めて食べた時に、優しく持とうと思ったんだけど、優しく持ったのに、ボロッボロになって...
Well, for sushi or macarons... when I first ate a macaron, I thought I'd hold it gently, but even though I held it gently, it crumbled into pieces...
そのエピソード大好き！かわいいな〜。
I love that episode! So cute.
あの、この中にある「お弁当のスプーン」ってやつなんですけど、これラミィの企画に前にかなたんが出てくれた時に、
Um, about the "lunchbox spoon" on this list, when Kanata appeared in my project before,
あの楽屋で出るお弁当かカレーだったんだけど、その時のスプーンを...
it was either a lunchbox or curry we had in the dressing room, and the spoon then...
バキって壊しちゃって。
She snapped it.
折れたんだよ勝手に。普通に食べてるだけでスプーン壊してて。
It just broke on its own. I was just eating normally and the spoon broke.
そうなんです。そう、びっくりしましたね。
Exactly. Yeah, I was surprised.
家ではあれですか、石のスプーンとか使ってる？
Do you use like... stone spoons at home?
石のスプーン違いますよ。鉄すら壊す。
Not stone spoons. I break even metal.
ま、あのーちゃんと割り箸とかね、使いますけど、たまに割り箸も割れるけど。
Well, I use disposable chopsticks properly, though sometimes they break too.
そうですね、スプーン真っ二つ事件は楽屋でこれやったのは2回ありますね。
Yeah, the "spoon snapped in half" incident happened twice in the dressing room.
やば〜い！
That's crazy!
そしてちょっと前、配信の流れで握力を計測した結果がこちらでございます。ほお。
And a little while ago, during a stream, we measured her grip strength, and here is the result. Oh.
やばー！！えぇ〜〜！！！
Crazy!! What?!!
55.9kgですね。
55.9kg.
ゴリラやん！やばっ！
She's a gorilla! Crazy!
これは配信でお酒を珍しく飲んだ時に、酔ってリミッター外れてんじゃない？みたいなノリで、
This was during a rare stream where I was drinking alcohol. In the heat of the moment, someone asked if my limiter was off because I was drunk.
あるので握力計が僕のお家にあるので、測ってみたんですけど、55.9kgの新記録が出まして。
I have a dynamometer at home, so I tried measuring, and I got a new record of 55.9kg.
これはですね、レスリングの霊長類最強女子の吉田沙保里さんが、あるテレビ番組で計測したのが55kgだったと。
This is... Yoshida Saori, the strongest primate woman in wrestling, measured 55kg on a TV show.
おいおいおいおい、やべーよ、超えとるやん！それ超えてます！
Wait, wait, wait, that's crazy, she surpassed her! I surpassed that!
ちょっと握手してみます？
Want to try shaking hands?
いやいや、怖い怖い。
No, no, that's scary.
ラミィ、ラミィ...
Lamy, Lamy...
前に握手したことあるんで。
I've shaken hands before.
あ、ね。新人ちゃん。
Ah, right. Newbie.
え、あの、リリカ握力7kgだったんですけど...
Um, Ririka's grip strength was 7kg...
本気で来てください。壊す気で来てください。
Please come at me for real. Come at me with the intent to break me.
8倍...いきますよ。8倍。
8 times... here I go. 8 times.
もっと本気で来い！
Come at me harder!
あ〜〜〜〜！！う、腕がぁぁぁ！
Aaaaah!! My... my arm!!
力の入れ方ってものを教えてやる。
I'll teach you how to apply force.
怖い怖い、やめて！やめてください！
Scary, scary, stop! Please stop!
リリカ大丈夫？動く？
Ririka, are you okay? Does it move?
大丈夫です。なめてました。
I'm okay. I underestimated her.
もうちょっとで壊すところでしたね。
I was about to break it.
本当にホロメンは力の弱い子が多いので、僕がおかしいような雰囲気がよく漂いますが...
There are really a lot of physically weak girls in Hololive, so there's often an atmosphere like I'm the weird one...
おかしいけどな。
You ARE weird though.
ま、そしてそんなね、キャラとツッコミキャラ、大きなターニングポイントとなりました。
Well, and those characters and my straight man character became a big turning point.
このツッコミキャラなんですけど、当時マインクラフトのホロサバ内に「かなた城」、お城を建設していた僕なんですけど、
About this straight man character, back then I was building "Kanata Castle" in the Hololive Minecraft server,
それを見たフレア先輩が「かなた学校建設予定地」と看板を書きました。学校に見えたんですよね。
and Flare-senpai saw it and wrote a sign saying "Kanata School Construction Site." It looked like a school to her.
「学校じゃねーからこれ！」と思わず言ったと。
"It's not a school!!" I said instinctively.
そしたらみこ先輩も来て「AO入学可能」と。で、学校いじりのボケが続いたので、「学校じゃねーよ！」とツッコミ続けたと。
Then Miko-senpai came and wrote "AO admission possible." Since the school jokes continued, I kept retorting, "It's not a school!!"
で、リスナーも喜んでくれまして、この時に気づいたことがあります。次のページ。
And the listeners were happy too, and I realized something then. Next page.
ホロライブにはボケが多い！
There are a lot of funny people in Hololive!
分かる～！
I get it!
そうなんですよ。
That's right.
ボケ属性のホロメンが非常に多いんですよ。
There are a lot of Hololive members with "boke" attributes.
ということでね、僕はこうなります。
So, here's what happens to me.
次のページ。
Next page.
クセつよだらけのホロライブ、「ツッコミ属性」に一筋の光！
In Hololive, full of strong personalities, a ray of light in the "tsukkomi attribute"!
おおー！
Ohhh!
そうなんです。僕はここからツッコミについて学び出します。
That's right. From here, I start learning about tsukkomi.
真面目に学び出しましてね。
I started learning it seriously.
あの、まあちゃんとツッコミできるようになったら、すごい役割的にもいいのかなと思って。
I thought it would be good for my role if I could do proper tsukkomi.
テレビを見て参考にしたツッコミ芸人の方がいらっしゃいます。
There is a tsukkomi comedian I looked up to on TV for reference.
その方がこちら。
Here they are.
次のページ。
Next page.
くりぃむしちゅーの上田さん！
Ueda-san from Cream Stew!
おおー！なるほど！
Ohhh! I see!
確かに確かに、ツッコミだよね。
True, true. He's definitely a tsukkomi.
あの、「しゃべくり007」とかを見てて、面白いなあと思って。
I watched shows like "Shabekuri 007" and thought he was funny.
上田さんを参考にツッコミを結構勉強しましたね。
I studied tsukkomi a lot using Ueda-san as a reference.
例えツッコミが多くて、すごく難しいんですけど。
He uses a lot of metaphorical tsukkomi, which is very difficult.
でもやっぱりこんな風になりたいなと思いながら勉強いたしました。
But I studied while wishing I could be like him.
まあ元々一方的に喋ってしまう、
I used to just talk one-sidedly,
オウム返しする、みたいなことがあったんですけど。
or just parrot what others said.
ツッコミを意識してからは、しっかり相手の言葉を聞いたり、待つこともできるようになりました。
Since focusing on tsukkomi, I've become able to listen carefully and wait for my turn.
すごーい！素晴らしい！
Amazing! Wonderful!
感動！
I'm moved!
こうして僕はツッコミで自分のポジションを開拓していくこととなります。
And so, I started to carve out my own position with tsukkomi.
ここまでの教訓としましては、次のページ。
As for the lesson so far... Next page.
自然とキャラはついてくる！
Characters will come naturally!
焦って無理しても空回りするだけ。
If you rush and force it, you'll just be spinning your wheels.
なるほどー。
I see.
無理してキャラ付けしなくても、勝手についていってその方が自分も楽だと。
Even if you don't force a persona, it'll stick on its own, and that's easier for you.
配信の中でね、自然と自分に合ったキャラがついてくるのでね。
In your streams, a character that suits you will naturally develop.
焦らずホロメンと喋ったり、配信のやり方、いいやり方を見つけるのがいいんじゃないかなと思います。
So I think it's best to just talk to members and find your own style without rushing.
ね、やっぱりキャラをどうしようとか、自分の理想もあるし、求められるものの違いとかあると思うんだけど。
You might worry about your persona or have ideals, and there might be expectations...
一番やりやすいのが、日々配信をたくさんするので絶対いいです。
But the easiest way is to just do a lot of daily streams.
今「キャラ無い」とか思っても、いつか絶対ついていくから。
Even if you think you don't have a persona now, one will definitely stick eventually.
本当にね、大丈夫ですと。
Really, it'll be fine.
いや、この配信マジで、
Seriously, this stream...
全ホロライブの新人に見せる会やったほうがいいです！マジで！
...should be shown to all Hololive newcomers! Seriously!
間違いないよ。
No doubt about it.
まず入ったら、この配信を見てもらう。とりあえず見ろ、つって。
First thing after joining, watch this stream. Just tell them "Watch it."
という感じで、こうして配信にもだんだん慣れていった僕ですが、
And so, as I gradually got used to streaming,
元々ホロライブに入ってやりたかったことがありました。
there was something I originally wanted to do when I joined Hololive.
次のページ。
Next page.
歌です。
Singing.
おお、歌ね。
Oh, singing.
イメージある。
I can see that.
ありがとうございます。子供の頃からアイドルに憧れ続けておりまして。
Thank you. I've been looking up to idols ever since I was a kid.
パワーポイントデビュー配信でも、ライブでコール＆レスポンスするのが目標、と言っていたりしました。
Even in my PowerPoint debut stream, I said my goal was to do call-and-response at a live.
当時は明確な目標はなく、いつかソロライブできたらな、っていう感じだったし、
At the time, I didn't have a clear goal, just a vague hope of doing a solo live someday...
そんなすぐにとも思ってなかったりですと。
...and I didn't think it would happen so soon.
まあね、歌が大好きな僕は、2020年の7月くらいから、
Well, loving singing as I do, from around July 2020,
月曜日の夜に毎週歌枠をやろうと思ってやってました。
I decided to do a singing stream every Monday night.
これは、いろんな方に歌聴いて欲しいとか、
This was because I wanted many people to hear my singing,
歌上手くなりたい、とか。
and I wanted to get better at it.
まあ、そういうこと思ってやってたので、自分でもすごく楽しみにしていた歌枠だったんですけど。
I did it with those thoughts, so I was really looking forward to it myself.
そんな僕に異変が起きます。
But then, something unusual happened to me.
なん だ？
What?
次のページ。
Next page.
耳の持病が悪化。
My ear condition worsened.
えー。これどんな症状だったんでしたっけ？
Oh... what kind of symptoms were they?
これはね、あの、まあ元々デビュー前から、
Well, even from before my debut,
ちょっと高い音が聞こえにくいとか、あとは低音が聞こえにくいとか色々あったんですけど。
I had various issues, like high sounds or low sounds being hard to hear.
もうこの頃はちょっと悪化しまして。
But around that time, it worsened.
片方の耳はほぼ聞こえてない。
I could barely hear out of one ear.
で、聞こえてないけど常に耳鳴りがいつもしてたり、
And though I couldn't hear, there was constant ringing...
何かあの特定の音が割れて聞こえるような状態になっておりまして。
...and certain sounds would sound distorted to me.
耳が聞こえづらいと歌にどんな影響が出てしまうのか？ 次のページ。
What impact does hearing difficulty have on singing? Next page.
自分の歌声がわからない。
I can't understand my own singing voice.
なんか、自分が歌ってる音程も、ちょっとずれて聞こえる時があるし、
Sometimes, the pitch I'm singing at sounds off to me...
声の大きさがわからなくて、大きく出しちゃうんだよね。力んじゃう、とか。
...and I can't tell the volume of my voice, so I end up singing too loud. I strain myself.
うまく歌えなくて、すごくこう、難しい。
Not being able to sing well was very... difficult.
となると、まああれだけ好きだった歌がね、まあやっぱり嫌いになってくるんですよ。
When that happens, the singing I loved so much... I start to hate it.
うまく歌えないなーってなって、歌わないと、
Thinking "I can't sing well," if I don't sing,
喉の筋肉も終わっていき、どんどん下手になって、あーもう嫌だと。
my throat muscles deteriorate, I get worse and worse, and I just feel done with it.
そしてまあお医者さんからも「1回お休みしたほうがいいんじゃないか」と言われた結果、
And after my doctor told me, "Maybe you should take a break for a while,"
次のページ。
next page.
毎週やっていた歌枠が終了します。
my weekly singing streams came to an end.
悲しいよ。
That's sad.
はい。ちょっとここはね、悲しいとこなんですけど、すごい悲しかったですね。
Yes. It's a sad part, and it was really sad for me.
まあ歌にハンデがあるっていうのはしょうがないとは思いつつ、なんでこういう自分なのかなって風に落ち込んだ時期もありました。
While I knew having a handicap in singing couldn't be helped, there were times I felt depressed, wondering why I was like this.
が、しかし、そんな時に支えになったのがこちら。次のページ。
But, however, what supported me during those times was this. Next page.
リスナーの温かい言葉と仲間のホロメンです。
The warm words from listeners and my Hololive companions.
あったかーい。
So warm.
いやもう本当に助かりましたね。やっぱりみんなに支えてもらって、
They really helped me. Having everyone support me,
時間がかかっても頑張ろうかなって思えてきまして。
I started to feel like I could keep trying, even if it takes time.
どんどん上がっていきましたね、モチベーション。
My motivation started going up and up.
よかった～！すごい！
That's good! Amazing!
1番大好きな音楽が嫌いになって、趣味が1個なくなったって思ってたんですけど...
I thought I'd come to hate my favorite thing, music, and lost a hobby...
リスナーさんから
From listeners,
「それでも歌大好きだよ」って言ってもらえて
being told "I still love your singing,"
「あ、まだやってもいいのかな」とか思えましたし
it made me think, "Oh, maybe I can keep going,"
そういう風に、今絶対聞き苦しいのに
and truly, even though it must be
聴いてくれるみんなのために頑張りたいと
hard to hear right now, I wanted to do
思いましたね、心から。
my best for everyone who listens.
リスナーさんからの温かい言葉ってさ、心に残るし嬉しいよね。
Warm words from listeners really stay in your heart and make you happy, don't they?
嬉しい。ね。そうだよね。
They do. Yeah, they really do.
みんなあるよね、そういうことね。
Everyone has those moments.
めっちゃあります。
Absolutely.
ちょっと落ち込んだ時とかにエゴサして「今日も可愛かったな」とか
When I'm feeling a bit down, I'll search for myself and see comments like "She was cute today too" or
「いっぱい頑張ってるね」とか
"She's working so hard," and
そういう優しいコメント見るだけで胸がいっぱいになって
just seeing those kind comments fills my heart,
「また頑張ろう」って気持ちにマジでなれます。
and I truly feel like I can give it my all again.
ありがとう！
Thank you!
素敵だね。
That's wonderful.
ラミィも、自分の体調の悪化で配信がしばらくできなかった時期があるんだけど
I also had a period where I couldn't stream for a while due to my health worsening,
その間にリスナーさんがずっと「ラミィちゃんいつまでも待ってるからね」って
and during that time, listeners were constantly saying, "Lamy-chan, we'll wait for you forever" or
「体調よく治すように、ちゃんと今休むんだよ」って
"Make sure you rest well to recover,"
ずっと待っててくれて、実際復帰した時もみんな温かく
They waited for me the whole time, and when I actually came back, everyone was so warm,
「ラミィちゃん待ってたよ、良かったね」って出迎えてくれて
welcoming me back with "Lamy-chan, we've been waiting for you, glad you're back!"
リスナーさん、あの時はありがとう。雪民さんいつも大好きだよ。
Listeners, thank you for that time. Yukimin, I always love you.
おかゆ先輩もありますか？
How about you, Okayu-senpai?
おかゆ先輩は体調崩したこととかはないけど
I haven't really had health issues like that, but
やっぱりこうゲームやっててめっちゃ悲しいシーンが来て
when I'm playing a game and a really
エンエン泣いちゃったりして鼻ずっぴずぴになったりするんだけど
sad scene comes up, I'll end up crying my eyes out and my nose gets all sniffly,
「ゆっくりでいいよ」「ゆっくり鼻かんでいいよ」って
but they tell me "Take your time" or "It's okay to blow your nose,"
言ってくれる優しさを感じますね、いつも本当に。
I always feel their kindness, really.
ありがとね。
Thank you.
優しいね。
They're so kind.
あとはたくさんホロメンにも応援してもらって
And I also got a lot of support from other Hololive members,
例えばフレア先輩から「耳の病気とかハンデがあっても、
for example, Flare-senpai told me, "Even with
その上でも歌上手だからすごいよ！」って言ってもらったりして勇気づけられたりとか
your ear condition or any handicap, your singing is amazing!" which really encouraged me.
あとは同期の桐生ココというね、人がいたんですけれども、まあ今卒業してしまいましたが
Also, there was my gen-mate, Kiryu Coco... she's graduated now, but
当時一緒の家で同居していたので、僕が落ち込んでいる時、特に何か言うわけでもなく
we were living together at the time, so when I was feeling down, she wouldn't necessarily say anything special,
「あ、飯食う？」みたいな感じで
but she'd just be like, "Oh, wanna eat?"
ちょっと似てる。
That's a bit of an impression.
「飯食う？」みたいな感じで、一緒に何かの味噌汁食べたりとか
Like "Wanna eat?", we'd eat miso soup together or
午前3時にちょっとおやつ食べたりとか
have a snack at 3 AM...
そういうのができたのが、今思うとすごく助かりました。
Looking back, being able to do things like that was a huge help.
そんな時に大事件が起きます。
And then, a major incident occurs.
同期メンバーの「卒業」です。
The "graduation" of a gen-mate.
これはですね、4期生は元々、今は4人なんですけど5人おりまして
You see, Gen 4 originally had five members, though there are four of us now,
同期のもう本当に天才のように面白かった桐生ココがですね、卒業することになりました。
and my gen-mate Kiryu Coco, who was truly a genius-level comedian, was to graduate.
何より同居とかしてたりとか、生活を共にしたりっていうのもあって、色んな話も聞いていたし
More than anything, since we lived together and shared our daily lives, I'd heard many things from her,
仲もね、本当に一番良かったかなと思います。
and I think our bond was truly the strongest.
その時に、活動の先に求めるものとか、生活の感じとかも色々似ていて
At the time, what we sought beyond our activities and our lifestyles were very similar,
本当に気が合った。
we really clicked.
そんなココの卒業っていうのは、僕にとってもかなり大きい出来事でございました。
So Coco's graduation was an incredibly significant event for me as well.
で、ね、リリカは喋ったことないもんね。
And, well, Ririka, you've never spoken with her, right?
そうですね、リリカが入った時にはすでにご卒業されてたんですけど
That's right. She had already graduated by the time I joined,
伝説のドラゴンのイメージが本当にもうすごくて、「最強の人」っていうイメージがあります。
but the image of the "Legendary Dragon" is so strong; I see her as the "strongest person."
いや、そうだよね。僕たち、ココちゃんとかかなたんの前から入ってるメンバーから見ても
Yeah, that's true. Even for members like us who joined before Coco-chan or Kanatan,
やっぱりココちゃんはすごい伝説をね、残していったなっていう印象ありますよ。
the impression remains that Coco-chan left behind an incredible legend.
4期生がホロライブに入って、ARKとかね、あさココとかも、毎日胸がドキドキするような時期だったし
When Gen 4 joined Hololive, with things like ARK and AsaCoco, it was a time of daily excitement,
毎日の朝のライブ配信とか、他のホロメンの情報まとめてニュースでやるっていうのがすごく斬新で
and her daily morning streams, summarizing news about other Hololive members, were so innovative,
天才だったなって今も思います。
I still think she was a genius.
準備とかも大変な中、そういうことをやって、箱のためになったらいいとかをすごく考える人でしたね。
Despite the difficult preparation, she did those things while thinking deeply about what would benefit the group.
そんな風に仲が良かったからこそ、卒業をすることがもう完全に決まったっていう時は
Because we were so close, when her graduation was finally and completely decided,
やっぱり悲しい気持ちはもちろんありました。
there was, of course, a feeling of sadness.
その時に、ココの卒業を聞いた僕は、最後にやりたかったことがありました。
At that time, upon hearing of Coco's graduation, there was one thing I wanted to do at the very end.
それがこちら、次のページ。
And that's this, on the next page.
4期生としてのオリジナル楽曲。
An original song for Gen 4.
せっかくなら5人のオリジナル曲欲しいよなって思ったんですよね。
I thought, since we have the chance, I really want an original song for the five of us.
そこで運営さんに「4期生の曲作りたい」と言うと、こう言われます。次。
When I told management, "I want to make a song for Gen 4," this is what they said. Next.
「間に合いません」
"It won't be in time."
時間がね。
Because of the time...
曲の制作には時間かかりますし、卒業が決まった時には「今からの楽曲制作は間に合わない」とはっきり言われました。
Song production takes time, and when the graduation was decided, I was told clearly that "starting production now won't be in time."
これを言われた僕はこう思います。
Having been told that, I thought...
だったら自分で作っちゃおう。
Then I'll just make it myself.
すごい！ / よくそうなった。
Amazing! / How did it come to that?
発注すると間に合わないなら
If commissioning it won't be in time,
発注すると間に合わないなら、自分で作れば間に合うだろうと思って、
I figured that if it wouldn't be ready in time if I ordered it, I'd just make it myself,
初めての作詞作曲をします。で、こうしてできた楽曲が次のページ。
so I tried my hand at songwriting for the first time. The resulting song is on the next page.
4期生5人で歌う最初で最後のオリジナル楽曲『キセキ結び』となります。
This is the first and last original song sung by the five of us in the 4th gen: 'Kiseki Musubi'.
はい。こちらね、当時の僕が思いを込めて、
Yes. I put all my feelings into this back then,
いろんな方に協力していただいて完成し、発表することができました。
and with the help of many people, I was able to complete and release it.
映像があるのでご覧ください。
We have a video, so please take a look.
約束しよう 僕ら出会えたキセキ
Let's make a promise, the miracle of our meeting,
忘れないように
so we never forget it.
夢抱いて集う 青春アニメみたいな
Gathering with dreams, like a youth anime,
ハッピーエンドになる 彼方へ飛ぶよ
we'll fly toward a happy ending, far away.
寝ぼけ眼あくびして 今日は何をしようか？
Yawning with sleepy eyes, what shall we do today?
永久に続く海を 駆け抜ける
Running through the eternal ocean.
今はため息 よりも勇気を
Now, instead of sighs, give us courage.
諦めるなんてないの ここで歌う
There's no giving up, we'll sing right here.
僕の声は聞こえてますか？ 君に届け
Can you hear my voice? Let it reach you.
学校の友達じゃ きっとない出会いだった
A meeting that surely wouldn't have happened with school friends.
画面の先の遥か遠くまで
Reaching far beyond the screen.
ささくれた言葉も 誰かの笑顔になる
Even sharp words can become someone's smile.
それぞれの色で 星結ぶキセキ
With our respective colors, a miracle that connects stars.
キラキラ輝くステージに
On the sparkling stage,
連れてくよ
I'll take you there.
はい、ありがとうございました。
Yes, thank you very much.
めっちゃよかった〜
That was amazing!
ありがとうございました。
Thank you very much.
いや、もう本当にこれメロディも歌詞も良くて。
The melody and the lyrics are just so good.
本当に、この曲を作っていた当時、おかゆ先輩とめっちゃ遊んでて。
Actually, when I was writing this song, I was hanging out with Okayu-senpai all the time.
めっちゃ遊んでた。マジで毎日会ってたよね。
We were! We really saw each other every day.
その時かなたんが「僕今作詞 頑張ってて」って言っててさ。
At the time, Kanatan said, "I'm working hard on the lyrics right now."
それで完成した曲がさ、こんなにいい曲だからさ。
And then the finished song turned out to be so wonderful.
すっごい褒めてくれて。ありがとう、本当に。
You praised me so much. Thank you, really.
歌詞の中に、みんなの名前が入ってるって、もうエモエモすぎんか？
The fact that everyone's names are in the lyrics... isn't that just so emotional?
天才でしょ、これ。
This is genius.
いやいや、もう本当にいろんな人に助けていただいて、こうして世に送り出すことになったんですけれども、
No, no, I had help from so many people to release this into the world.
悲しんだりとか寂しがってるだけではいけないなと僕は思いました。
I thought that I couldn't just keep being sad and lonely.
この頃の人生グラフはこうなっております。次のページ。
My life graph at that time looked like this. Next page.
おー、上がってきた！上がった！
Oh! It's going up! It went up!
一回、周りと比較するより、過去の自分と比較するっていうのが一番いいよね、みたいな話をよくココともしていまして、
I often talked with Coco about how it's best to compare yourself to your past self rather than to others.
そういうことを続けて、とにかく自分を磨いていこうと思いました。
I decided to keep doing that and just focus on polishing myself.
それから改めて歌に力を入れていくんですが、ソロライブをやるにはどうすればいいか？っていうのを考えた時に、
After that, I redoubled my efforts in singing. When I thought about how to hold a solo live...
まずは「天音かなた＝歌」、そういう印象をつけようと思いました。
First, I wanted to establish the impression that "Amane Kanata = singing."
そのためにちょっと意識していたことがあります。それが次のページ。
To achieve that, there was something I was mindful of. That's on the next page.
他のメンバーのライブに、いっぱいゲストで出演させていただく。はい。
Appearing as a guest in many other members' lives. Yes.
当時、記念ライブにはホロメンをゲストで呼ぶっていうのが、今もですけど当たり前の時代だったので、
Back then, it was common—and still is—to invite Hololive members as guests to anniversary lives.
いただいたオファーもなるべく、本当にありがたい機会だということで、もちろん祝う気持ちが一番なんですけど、
So, I tried to accept as many offers as possible, seeing them as wonderful opportunities. Of course, celebrating them was the priority.
自分もいっぱい歌を歌いたい、もっと成長したいという思いで、オファーを片っ端から引き受けていきました。
With the desire to sing more and grow further, I accepted every offer that came my way.
さらにですね、こんなことをしてみます。次のページ。
And then, I did something like this. Next page.
2周年記念ライブで、ゲストなしのソロライブを行いました。はい。
For my 2nd anniversary concert, I performed a solo live with no guests. Yes.
この自分のデビュー2周年記念ライブの「リベンジ」というものでは、ゲストがいるのが当たり前の時代に、
In my 2nd anniversary live "Revenge," in an era where having guests was the norm,
ソロライブをする人が逆、いなくなってたんですけれども、
people doing solo lives had actually become rare.
あえてゲストを呼ばず、1時間で15曲も歌うライブを、ちょっと挑戦的にやってみたりもしました。
I challenged myself by not inviting guests and singing 15 songs in one hour.
この頃から自分の歌についても真剣に向き合うようになっていくんですが、
From around that time, I started to take my own singing more seriously.
僕は一から発声や歌い方を見直すことになります。
I decided to re-examine my vocalization and singing style from scratch.
ここでですね、やったことがこちら。次のページ。
And here's what I did. Next page.
自分の歌い方の「癖」の選別、
Screening the "quirks" of my singing,
人気曲のボーカルだけを抽出して分析、昔の曲の研究、というのをやりました。
extracting and analyzing vocals from popular songs, and researching old songs.
気になることがいっぱいある... 「歌い方の癖の選別」って何？
There's so much I'm curious about... What's "screening the quirks of your singing"?
天音かなたがやった歌の研究
Kanata Amane's Research on Singing
この癖なんですけど...
About these singing habits...
自分の歌い方の「癖」の選別
Selecting vocal habits/quirks
強い癖があったほうが個性があっていいとか、
Some say having strong quirks is good for individuality,
強い癖 → 個性があっていい
Strong habits -> Good individuality
癖がないほうが聞きやすいよとかあったんですけど、
while others say having no quirks makes it easier to listen to.
癖がない → 聞きやすい
No habits -> Easy to listen to
まずは自分はやっぱり癖はどちらかというと強いから、
Since my own habits were on the stronger side,
自分の癖はどちらかというと強いから
Because my habits are rather strong
じゃあどこを残そうかと考えた時に、
when I thought about which parts to keep,
どこを残そうかと考えた時に
When I thought about which parts to keep
まずは癖をゼロにしようと思いまして。
I decided to first reset my habits to zero.
まずは癖をゼロにしよう
First, let's reset habits to zero
あの、ちょうど「歌ってみた」の「炉心融解」とかボーカロイドの曲歌ったんですけど、
I sang Vocaloid songs like 'Meltdown' for 'Utattemita' covers,
「炉心融解」とかボーカロイドの曲歌ったんですけど
I sang Vocaloid songs like 'Meltdown'
その時とかも癖ゼロでボカロみたいに歌うことを意識したりしました。
and at that time, I focused on singing like a Vocaloid with zero habits.
癖ゼロでボカロみたいに歌うことを意識したりしました
I made a conscious effort to sing like a Vocaloid with zero habits
いい癖は残して、ま、ちょっと聞きにくいなって癖はなるべくなくすっていうことで、
I aimed to keep the good habits and eliminate the difficult-to-hear ones,
いい癖は残して聞きにくい癖はなるべくなくす
Keep good habits and eliminate difficult-to-hear ones as much as possible
ちょっとブラッシュアップをしていこうと思ってましたね。
and worked on brushing up my style.
いや、でも思った。一時期の時からかなたんの歌い方変わったなって思った。
Yeah, I noticed that. I felt like Kanatan's singing style changed at some point.
一時期の時からかなたんの歌い方変わったな
Kanata's singing style changed at one point
え、そうなんですよ。おかゆ先輩ともね、いっぱい歌ってみた歌わせていただいたりしてるんですけど、
Oh, that's true. I've done many covers with Okayu-senpai, but...
その初期の頃歌ってみたやってる時はまだ選別前で、
when I was doing covers early on, it was before the selection process,
初期の頃歌ってみたやってる時はまだ選別前で
Back when I did 'Utattemita' covers early on, it was before the selection process
声がちょっとブスの時...
so my voice was a bit 'ugly' then...
（声が）ちょっとブスの時
When my (voice) was a bit ugly
ちょいブスの時ね。そんなこともあった。
Back when it was a bit unpolished. That was a thing.
ちょいブスの時ね
Back when it was a bit ugly
そんなことないですよ！
That's not true at all!
みたいな感じで。ただこれは、結構辛い作業で、
Like that. However, this was a pretty tough task,
辛い作業で1年かかりまして
It was a tough task that took a year
これ実は1年かかりまして。選びましたね。
it actually took a year. I made my selections.
あと、人気曲... ま、例えばYOASOBIさんとかの流行りのアーティスト...
Also, popular songs... like from trending artists like YOASOBI...
YOASOBIさんとか流行りのアーティスト
Trending artists like YOASOBI
やっぱり流行りの歌い方っていうものがあるなっていうのを感じて、
I felt that there's definitely a 'trending style' of singing,
流行りの歌い方っていうものがある
There's such a thing as a trending singing style
あの、そういう方々のボーカルを聴いて、
so I listened to their vocals and thought,
そういう方々のボーカルを聞いて
Listening to those people's vocals
「こういう癖は入れるけど、ここにはこれを入れないんだ」とか、
'I'll include this quirk here, but I won't put this one here,'
こういう癖は入れるけどここにはこれを入れないんだとか
Deciding things like "I'll put in this quirk, but I won't put this one here"
そういうのを研究というか、分析しましたね。
and researched, or rather, analyzed them.
研究というか分析しましたね
I researched, or rather, analyzed them
勉強熱心や。
How studious.
流行りっていうのがありつつも、
While there are trends,
流行りがありつつも寄せるか寄せまいか考えました
While there are trends, I thought about whether to mimic them or not
そこに寄せるか寄せまいかっていうのはすごく考えましたね。
I thought hard about whether to lean into them or not.
あとは、昔の歌も研究して。
I also researched older songs.
曲にも、こう、流行りの周期があって、
Songs also have cycles of trends,
曲にも流行りの周期があって
Songs also have cycles of trends
曲のなんかこうロックっぽいのが流行ったり、バラードが流行ったりとか。
like rock-ish styles being popular, or ballads being popular.
ロックっぽいのが流行ったりバラードが流行ったり
Rock-ish ones being popular, ballads being popular...
今はこうちょっとエモ系だったり。
Nowadays, it's more 'emo' styles.
エモ系だったり
And 'emo' styles...
この昔流行った曲とか、その時に流行ってる歌い方とかもかなり研究を。
I researched older hits and the singing styles popular at those times as well.
昔流行った曲とかその時に流行ってる歌い方もかなり研究を
I researched older hits and the singing styles popular at those times as well
本当すごい。
That's truly amazing.
なんかさっきツッコミも、その、色々勉強されてたみたいな話もあったし、
We heard earlier that you also studied how to do comedy retorts,
ツッコミも色々勉強されてた
She also studied comedy retorts (tsukkomi)
今回もこう、色々研究して、本当に努力家というか...
and with all this research too, you're a real hard worker...
今回もいろいろ研究して本当に努力家
She researched a lot this time too, she's really a hard worker
本当だよね。積み重ねがすごいわ、かなた。
It's true. Your dedication is incredible, Kanata.
ありがとう、120点のコメント。えへ。
Thank you for that 120-point comment. Ehe.
ありがとう120点のコメント
Thank you for the 120-point comment
で、とにかくこれほどしないと、自分の、ま、耳の癖もありますし、
Anyway, without going this far, because of my own listening habits,
ちょっと聞きづらくなってる歌っていうのが、なかなか変えられないなっていうことで1からやろうと思って。
it was hard to change the way I sang. So I decided to start from scratch.
聞きづらくなってる歌がなかなか変えられない
Songs that have become hard to listen to are difficult to change
これをやった結果、昔3時間かかっていたレコーディングが、今は20分くらいで終わるように...
As a result, recording that used to take 3 hours now finishes in about 20 minutes.
3時間かかっていたレコーディングが今は20分くらいで終わる
Recordings that used to take 3 hours now finish in about 20 minutes
すごーい！はや〜！
Amazing! So fast!
なりました。ありがとうございます。
That's how it is now. Thank you.
ま、これもレコーディングをやる時に、「この癖を入りたいな」って何度も何度も試すとかやってたんですけど、
I used to try over and over during recording, thinking 'I want to add this quirk,'
この癖を入れたいなって何度も試すとかやってた
I used to try putting in this habit over and over again
それがパッてできるようになったっていう。
but now I can do it instantly.
それがパッてできるようになった
Now I can do it instantly
納得できる歌い方ができるようになった、っていう感じでしたね。
I became able to sing in a way I'm satisfied with.
納得できる歌い方ができるようになった
I became able to sing in a way I'm satisfied with
みなさんはレコーディングにこだわりってありますか？
Does everyone have preferences for recording?
こだわりというか、今現在、まさにその、自分の癖で悩んでて。
It's not so much a preference, but right now I'm actually struggling with my own habits.
こだわりというか今現在まさに自分の癖で悩んでて
It's not so much a preference, but right now I'm actually struggling with my own habits
そうなんだ。
Is that so?
なんか、歌って今までやってこなかったんだけど、
I haven't really sung much until now,
ホロライブに入って歌う機会がすごく増えて
The opportunities to sing increased significantly after joining Hololive
ホロライブに入って歌を歌う機会がすごく増えて、
but after joining Hololive, my opportunities to sing have increased significantly,
初めて自分の癖みたいなのが出てきちゃってる
My own quirks are starting to show for the first time
初めて自分の癖みたいなのが出てきちゃってるの、逆に。
and conversely, my own quirks are starting to show for the first time.
ほぉ〜、なるほど。
Oh, I see.
それを残したほうがいいのか、省いてもっとまっさらな歌い方にしたらいいのか、
I'm wondering if I should keep them or get rid of them for a 'blank slate' style,
それを残したほうがいいのかまっさらな歌い方にしたらいいのか
Should I keep them or go for a clean slate singing style?
すごいリアルタイムで悩んでて。
and I'm struggling with that right now.
すごいリアルタイムで悩んでて
I'm struggling with it right now
ちょっとこの件かなたんに相談します。
I'll consult Kanata about this later.
この件かなたんに相談します
I'll consult Kanata about this
待ってます！相談室、空きあるからね。
I'm waiting! My consulting room is always open.
待ってます！
I'm waiting!
二人は？
What about the two of you?
え、リリカは、なんか感情が死んでるのか分かんないんですけど...
Well, for Ririka, I don't know if my emotions are dead, but...
感情が死んでるのか分かんない
I don't know if my emotions are dead
どういうこと？
What do you mean?
歌う時に、やっぱり感情を乗せるのがあんまり得意じゃなくて。
When I sing, I'm just not very good at putting emotion into it.
歌う時に感情を乗せるのがあんまり得意じゃなくて
I'm not very good at putting emotion into it when I sing
その歌詞の意味とかが、多分頭をこう、すーって通り抜けちゃうんですよね。
The meaning of the lyrics just kind of passes right through my head.
歌詞の意味とかが頭を通り抜けちゃうんです
The meaning of the lyrics just passes through my head
あぁ〜。
Ahhh...
なるべくどういう情景かとかを思い描きながら、歌うように頑張ってるんで、
I'm trying to sing while imagining the scene as much as possible,
なるべく情景を思い描きながら歌うように頑張ってるんで
I'm trying to sing while imagining the scene as much as possible
まずはね、ちょっと感情を取り戻すところから頑張りたいと思います。
so I'll start by trying to recover my emotions.
感情を取り戻すところから
Starting by recovering my emotions
元々なくなってる？
Were they gone to begin with?
なくなってる
They're gone
化け物かもしれない。
She might be a monster.
化け物かもしれない
I might be a monster
そんなことはないですよ。
That's not true at all.
そんなことはない
That's not true
おかゆ先輩、感情入れて歌うの得意な気がしますけど。
Okayu-senpai, I feel like you're good at singing with emotion.
おかゆ先輩 感情入れて歌うの得意な気がしますけど
Okayu-senpai, I feel like you're good at singing with emotion
あ、ホント？僕やかなたんってさ、ま、ミックスの勉強もしてたことあったじゃん。
Oh, really? Well, you and I have both studied mixing before, right?
ミックス レコーディングされた複数の音のバランスを調整しまとめ上げる作業
Mixing: The process of adjusting the balance of multiple recorded sounds and compiling them
あ、そうですね。
Ah, that's right.
だからこう、ミックスするとどうしても表情感って消えやすいから。
Because when you mix, expressiveness tends to get lost.
ピッチの補正でね。
Because of pitch correction.
ピッチ 音の高さ
Pitch: The height of sound
ピッチの補正でね
With pitch correction
そうそう。補正で消えるんだよ。
Exactly. It disappears with correction.
補正で消えるんだよ
It disappears with correction
だから、そのピッチを取るか表現を取るか、みたいなことは結構考えること多いかもね。
So we might often have to choose between perfect pitch and expression.
ピッチを取るか表現を取るか考えること多いかもね
We might often think about choosing between pitch and expression
いや、大事やな。
Yeah, that's important.
大事やな
That's important
そうだね、なんか音程を気にするとやっぱり表情が落ちていくっていうのは絶対あるから、
Right, focusing too much on pitch definitely causes expressiveness to drop.
音程を気にすると表情が落ちていくのは絶対ある
Focusing on pitch definitely causes expression to drop
そうだね。
That's true.
1個だけ、「この1行めっちゃいいからここだけ入れよう」とか決めると、めっちゃやりやすいかも。
It might be easier if you decide, 'This one line is great, so I'll put expression just here.'
この1行めっちゃいいからここだけ入れようとか決めるとやりやすい
It's easier if you decide, "This line is great, so I'll put expression just here"
え、めっちゃ勉強になる！タメになる〜。
Whoa, that's so helpful! I learned a lot!
めっちゃ勉強になる！
That's so helpful!
タメになる〜
This is useful...
と言いつつ、ま、僕もまだまだなんでございますが、
That said, I still have a long way to go,
地道な活動の結果
The result of steady efforts
ま、こうした地道な活動の結果、2022年の年末に行われた3周年記念ライブ『別世界』ではこうなります。
but as a result of these steady efforts, this is how it turned out at my 2022 3rd Anniversary Live, 'Betsu Sekai'.
2022年の年末に行われた3周年記念ライブ『別世界』ではこうなります
This is how it turned out at the 3rd Anniversary Live "Betsu Sekai" held at the end of 2022
次のページ、んっ。
Next page, there.
21秒のロングトーンの歌が大反響！
The song with the 21-second long tone was a huge hit!
21秒のロングトーン 歌が大反響
The 21-second long tone song was a huge hit
すごーい！
Amazing!
すごいんだから。
It's truly incredible.
すごいんだから
It's amazing
このライブの、え、ロングトーン部分の映像があるみたいなのでご覧ください。
There seems to be footage of the long tone part of this live, so please take a look.
よろしければご覧ください。どうぞ！
Please watch if you'd like. Here you go!
おおー
Ooh~
ショートとかでもめっちゃ流れてくるからね。
It pops up in Shorts all the time, too.
いや、そうなのよ。そうそう。
Yeah, that's true. Exactly.
僕じゃない人がショートたくさん切り抜いてるんですよね。
People who aren't me are clipping it for Shorts a lot.
すごいからね。
Because it's amazing.
驚異の、みたいな。
Like 'Incredible performance' or something.
何回も見たくなる。
You want to watch it over and over.
やばい、もう息した！
Whoa, she just took a breath!
そうそう、息した息した。
Yeah, yeah, she took a breath.
もう吸いたい、吸いたい。
I want to breathe too, I want to breathe.
もう、喉苦しい、喉苦しい。
Ugh, my throat hurts just watching.
こっから！
From here!
上がるのがすごいのよ。
The way it goes up is incredible.
本当にそう。
It really is.
上がる！？ってなるからね。
You're like, 'It's going up!?'
どうやってー？
How is she doing that?
まじでやばい。
Seriously crazy.
で、最後のビブラートで、
And with that final vibrato...
まだ残ってたんや！ってなる。
You're like, 'She still had some left!?'
すごい技術だよ。
That's incredible technique.
いやいやいや。本当にね、とんでもなく練習したんですけども。
No, no. I really practiced an insane amount.
あの、これは実は元をたどると、ちょっと逃げのロングトーンで...
Actually, if you go back to the source, that long tone was a bit of a cop-out...
えぇ！？
Eh!?
なぜ逃げだったかというと、
As for why it was a cop-out,
どこに逃げたの？
Where did you run to?
あの、この「unravel」という楽曲、ここでデスボが本家だと、
In this song 'unravel', the original has a death growl here,
「ヴォーーー」って出るの。
That goes 'Vooooo' like that.
それができないんで、ロングトーンにした。
I couldn't do that, so I made it a long tone instead.
っていうのが、実ははじめだったんです。
That's how it actually started.
逃げではない。
That's not a cop-out.
逃げてない、挑戦だよ、挑戦！
You're not running away, it's a challenge, a challenge!
デスボから逃げてきて、でロングトーンと、なったんですが。
I ran away from the death growl and it became a long tone, but...
ま、当時やりたいことをかなり詰め込んだライブが成功して。
Well, that live, where I packed in everything I wanted to do at the time, was a success.
100万人記念の新衣装もちょうど見せるタイミングだったり、
It was also the timing to show off my 1 million milestone outfit,
unravelでロングトーンしたことを、いろんな人に、本当に思った以上にいろんな方に見ていただいて。
And so many people, far more than I expected, saw me do that long tone in unravel.
「今までで一番ライブよかった！」っていう反響いただいたりとか、
I got feedback like, 'That was your best live ever!'
「歌上手くなったね」って言ってもらえるのがすごく嬉しくて、
It made me so happy to hear people say 'Your singing has improved,'
まだ頑張っていこうと思いました。
So I thought I'd keep doing my best.
この時の反響がなければ、今自分はね、必死に歌頑張るということはなかったかなと思います。
If it weren't for the reaction back then, I don't think I'd be working as hard as I am on my singing now.
で、その後ね、去年3月に、天音かなたファーストアルバムCDの「Unknown DIVA」を発表することもできまして。
And after that, in March last year, I was able to announce my first album CD, 'Unknown DIVA'.
見事完売できまして。
And it successfully sold out.
素晴らしい！すごーい！
Wonderful! Amazing!
運営さんもね、頑張ったと認めてくれたのかなっていうふうに感じましたし。
I felt like even the management recognized that I worked hard.
まぁ何より聞いたね、平民のみんなが嬉しそうにしてくれたり、
But more than anything, seeing my Heimin (fans) so happy after listening,
好きな曲を発見してくれたりして、僕もすごく嬉しかったです。
and discovering songs they liked, made me very happy too.
そしてなんと！
And what's more!
今年7月23日には！
On July 23rd this year!
セカンドアルバム「Trigger」を発売します！
I will be releasing my second album, 'Trigger'!
さらにさらに！
And further still!
8月13日は待望のソロライブを行わせていただくまでになります！
On August 13th, I'll even be holding my long-awaited solo live!
おめでとー！
Congratulations!
でもこのアルバムの「Trigger」は、ジャケットとかアナザージャケットっていうのを自分で発注からやって、
But for this album 'Trigger', I handled everything from ordering the jacket and alternative jackets myself,
クオリティに結構こだわっていたり。
and I'm pretty particular about the quality.
楽曲なんですけど「十万億土」という楽曲を、作詞作曲してみました。
As for the songs, I tried writing and composing a track called 'Juman Okudo'.
こちらもね、ラップを入れてみたり挑戦してみたので、ぜひチェックしてほしいです。
I challenged myself with things like adding rap to it, so I really want you to check it out.
めっちゃ楽しみ〜
I'm so looking forward to it~
他にも「世界で一番のアイドル」という楽曲の作詞もしままして、
I also wrote the lyrics for another song called 'The Best Idol in the World',
こちらはですね、先ほどの「十万億土」とは全く違く、もう素直な気持ちを。韻などは踏んでおりません！
And for this one, unlike 'Juman Okudo', it's just my honest feelings. No rhyming or anything like that!
素直な気持ちを文字にしたので、応援してくれる平民に届いたらいいなと思っております。
I put my honest feelings into words, so I hope it reaches the Heimin who support me.
絶対届くよ！
It'll definitely reach them!
全体的に歌がパワーアップしていると思いますので、ソロライブを楽しみにしていてほしいと思います！
I think my singing has powered up overall, so please look forward to the solo live!
そんな僕の現在のホロライブ人生グラフはこうなります。次のページ。
So, here is my current hololive life graph. Next page.
おおー！上がってる！すごい！
Oh! It's going up! Amazing!
上昇してる！
It's rising!
現在、右肩上がりで順調に行かせていただいております。
Currently, it's going smoothly with an upward trend.
いやもうそれもこれもね、ここに集まってくれた3人、本当に僕は心から感謝している。忙しい中来てもらって。
I'm truly grateful from the bottom of my heart to the three of you who gathered here. Thank you for coming despite your busy schedules.
カニが待っているからな。
Because the crab is waiting.
カニ食べたい〜！カニ〜！
I want to eat crab! Crab~!
奢りたいと思います。
I'd like to treat you all.
最後に僕のデビュー配信を振り返らせていただきますが、
Lastly, I'll look back at my debut stream,
僕はデビュー配信でこんなことを言っていました。こちら。
I said something like this in my debut stream. Here it is.
僕が初配信でこうやっていっぱい話した、突拍子もない夢を、
Those wild dreams I talked so much about during my first stream...
いつか叶えることができたら、
If I can ever make them come true,
それはまず、リスナーさん、へい民のみんなのおかげだから。
It will be, first and foremost, thanks to the listeners and all the Heimin.
こうして活動が始まったけど、最初から最後まで頑張って、
My activities have started, but I'll do my best from start to finish,
自分も皆も今より幸せになるように、
so that both I and everyone else can become happier than we are now.
それが天音かなたがVTuberとして活動する理由です。
That is the reason Amane Kanata is active as a VTuber.
すごいよ、初配信で。
That's amazing for a first stream.
えらいよ。しっかりしてるー。
You're so admirable. So level-headed.
まあ当時は突拍子もない夢だと思ってましたけど、
Well, back then I thought they were wild dreams, but...
本当にいろんな夢が叶うところまで来られた。
I've really come to the point where many of those dreams are coming true.
ということで、いろんなしくじりや事件があって紆余曲折しましたが、
So, after various failures and incidents, and many twists and turns,
今こうして天音かなたという僕出来上がりました。ありがとうございます。
I have become the Amane Kanata you see today. Thank you very much.
皆さん、今日の授業いかがだったでしょうか？
Everyone, how was today's lesson?
めっちゃ良かったよ。
It was really good.
超勉強になった。
I learned so much.
かなたんが努力の人っていうのが、この時間でものすごい分かったと思う。
I think everyone really saw in this time how much of a hard worker Kanatan is.
本当だよね。うんうん。
That's true. Yeah, yeah.
本当に。ありがとう。
Truly. Thank you.
いろんな苦労もあっただろうに、それを感じさせず...
You must have faced many hardships, yet you didn't let it show...
いやいやいや、もうもう、本当にね、僕はね、正直、
No, no, no, honestly, for me,
この授業をホロメン全員分見たいぐらいあります。
I want to see everyone in Hololive do their own version of this lesson.
みんなのこの人生を教えてくれ。
Please tell me about your lives.
ということでね、まあ歌の話もして、ちょっと実はね、
So, we talked about my singing, and actually...
まあはっきり言ってこれはね...
to be blunt, this is...
収録なんです。
...a recording.
えー！
What?!
はっきり言って収録だから、僕たち今過去から来ています。
To be clear, since it's a recording, we are coming from the past right now.
未来の僕、今ここから生でね、ちょっと続きの配信してくるので。
Future me is going to do a live stream continuing from right here.
じゃあ、未来に行ってくる！
Well then, I'm off to the future!
いってらっしゃい！
See you later!
あれ？置いていかれる感じで？
Wait? Are we being left behind?
あの、僕たちはこの後どうしたら？
Um, what should we do after this?
カニ行こうな！！
Let's go eat crab!!
いえーい！！カニ～～！！
Yay!! Crab~~!!
行ってくる～！
I'm off!
未来に！
To the future!
手詰まりな現状の行き場が
Stuck in a deadlock, nowhere to go
止めどない感情と交差する
Endless emotions intersect
どうしたってももう変えられない
No matter what, it can't be changed anymore
それはきっと個人の過護じゃない
Surely it's not due to an individual's failure
接吻（セルフ）助けが効くのは限られた範囲の話で
Self-help only works within a limited scope
そこを出しちゃとは不干渉
Stepping outside of that is non-interference
どうせ何をしたって正気がないんだって
Whatever you do, there's no hope anyway
自分がどう足掻こうたって
No matter how much you struggle
びくともしない机上の空論
Desk theories that won't budge an inch
それならこれ位の方法も
Then even a method like this
知らないからね
I wouldn't know
変わらない後悔があったとて
Even if there's unchanging regret
今更できることなんて何もないんだ
There's nothing left to do now
凄いとことか責めないで
Don't blame me for the great parts
決まりきった事実に抗いようもないで
There's no point resisting fixed facts
連絡していても最善手すら見つからんだ
Even if in contact, I can't even find the best move
今をもう捨て去るだろう
You'll probably cast away the present
そして徐々に心が軽くなってしまう
And gradually, your heart becomes lighter
認めきれない言葉の連鎖で
Through a chain of words I can't fully accept
きっと僕らは無力であって
Surely we are powerless
指導の行方が定まらないなら
If the direction of guidance is uncertain
いっそ何も分からないままで
Better to just stay not knowing anything
止まりきれない常識の尺度は
The scale of common sense that won't stop
絶対的に正しくない場
Is an absolutely incorrect place
僕の手に負えない君の脳裏は
Your mind that I can't handle
どうやっても救いやしない
I can't save it no matter what
君らが慈愛を請うたって
Even if you beg for mercy
正直役目の管轄外
To be honest, it's outside my jurisdiction
結局未来の想定も
In the end, even future expectations
セルフとなってます
Are becoming self-service
しようもない救済を待ってても
Even if waiting for a hopeless salvation
神様ごっこはやってこないし
Playing god won't help
時間が上手すぎるだけ
Time is just too good at it
止めどない思考事実を知らず
Unaware of the facts of endless thoughts
変わらない後悔があったとて
Even if there's unchanging regret
今更できることなんて何もないんだ
There's nothing left to do now
凄いとことか責めないで
Don't blame me for the great parts
決まりきった事実に抗いようもないで
There's no point resisting fixed facts
十人十色関係ない
Different strokes for different folks doesn't matter
今自分の事だけでいっぱいなんだ
I have my hands full with my own life right now
その場凌ぎの羽も退化し
Temporary makeshift wings also degenerate
既成の足で歩むしかないのだろう
I suppose I have no choice but to walk with established feet
みんな！見ましたか？
Everyone! Did you see?
みんな、帰ってきたよ。ちょっとこの教室で...
Everyone, I'm back. Back in this classroom...
はぁ、ちょっと一息...誰もいない。
Sigh, taking a breath... no one is here.
おい、勝手に帰った。いや、ありがとうございました。
Hey, they went home without me. Well, thank you very much.
ということで、すごかったよね。パチパチありがとう。
So, that was amazing, right? Thank you for the applause.
今歌った曲なんですが、新曲になります！
The song I just sang is actually a new song!
こちら、7月23日水曜日に発売予定の僕のセカンドアルバム『Trigger』から、
This is from my 2nd album 'Trigger', scheduled for release on Wednesday, July 23rd,
サツキさんに制作いただいた『セルフサービス』を初披露させていただきました。
I gave the first performance of 'Self Service', produced by Satsuki-san.
本日このあと21時からMVを公開、
The music video will be released at 9 PM today,
そして24時から各配信サービスにて音源リリース予定です！
and the song will be available on all streaming services from midnight!
そして！
And!
アルバム追加情報として、『Trigger』に収録されている全9曲の情報...
for more album information, here is the information for all 9 tracks included in 'Trigger'...
初公開！
First reveal!
今回も超豪華作家陣の皆様に
This time too, a super luxurious group of creators...
素敵な全9曲作っていただきました！
...have created 9 wonderful songs for me!
アルバムはアクスタ3種セットや
The album comes in a super deluxe limited edition including a set of 3 acrylic stands...
限定フォトカードが入っている超豪華な完全生産限定盤
...and limited photo cards...
そしてA・Bの2形態ご用意している通常盤の
...and then the regular editions available in two versions, A and B...
計3種が大・大・大・大好評...と言っておきますからね！
...a total of 3 types are - I'll say it now - super, super, super popular!
みんなよろしくお願いします！
Please look forward to it everyone!
予約受付中ですのでぜひぜひ手に入れてくださいね！
Pre-orders are open, so please make sure to get your hands on them!
そしてね、YouTubeご覧の皆様は
And for those watching on YouTube...
配信画面の下にタグ付けされている
...from the purchase button for the products tagged under the stream screen...
商品の購入ボタンからご予約できますのでチェックしてください！
...you can pre-order, so please check it out!
絶対頑張って設定したから多分いるはず！
I worked really hard on the settings, so they should be there!
そして！皆様お待ちかねの
And! The moment you've all been waiting for...
ソロライブの追加の告知でございます！
...it's the additional announcement for my solo live!
まずはお、ありがとね。
First... oh, thank you.
まずはこちらの動画をどうぞ！
First, please watch this video!
2025.8.13
Amane Kanata 1st Solo Live
狙いを定めたその先は、あなたの心
Aiming straight for your heart
楽曲一発一発に
Into every single song
"僕の感情"を込めて
I put my emotions
全力で撃ち抜いていく
I will shoot right through with all my might
LOOK ON
ARIAKE ARENA
一人ひとりの感情に、確かな共鳴（トリガー）が広がっていく
A certain resonance (trigger) spreads through each and every emotion
かっこいい！ということで
Cool! So...
今回のライブタイトルは
The title for this live is...
Amane Kanata 1st Solo Live 『LOCK ON』です！
Amane Kanata 1st Solo Live 'LOCK ON'!
2ndアルバム『Trigger』との繋がりも考えて
Thinking about the connection with the 2nd album 'Trigger'...
ライブでみんなをね、ガンガン撃ち抜いていくイメージでございます。
...it's with the image of shooting everyone down one by one at the live.
キービジュアルは現実世界に天界の門が降臨した
The key visual has an otherworldly atmosphere...
異世界感のある雰囲気になってます。
...like the gates of the celestial realm descending into the real world.
どうですか？このクールでかっこいい僕を見て
How is it? Seeing this cool and stylish me...
ライブへの期待感爆上がり？
...is your excitement for the live skyrocketing?
有明アリーナもね、皆様お待たせしました。
And the Ariake Arena... sorry to keep you waiting.
会場は有明アリーナで開催いたします！
The venue will be Ariake Arena!
本当にね、たくさんホロライブの先輩たちも
Really, many Hololive senpais...
こちらでね、ライブやってきているので頑張ろうと思います。
...have performed here, so I'll do my best.
今回のソロライブのハッシュタグはですね
The hashtag for this solo live is...
「#打ち抜けかなた」です！
'#UchinukeKanata'!
どんどんみんなポストして一緒にライブを盛り上げてくれ！
Everyone, please keep posting and let's get hyped for the live together!
そして、じゃじゃん！チケット情報はこちら！
And, ta-da! Here is the ticket information!
S席、A席、B席の3種類をご用意しました。
We have prepared three types of seats: S, A, and B.
1次先行はこのあと21時から申し込み開始となります！
First pre-order starts from 9:00 PM tonight!
これね、抽選なんでみんな慌てずに、大丈夫ですからね。
This is by lottery, so don't rush, it's okay.
今回はチケット販売サイトのZAIKOで
This time, on the ticket sales site ZAIKO...
海外の平民向けにも現地チケットを販売します！
...we'll also sell venue tickets for the overseas Heimin!
世界中のね、平民に会えるの楽しみにしてるからね、みんな！
I'm looking forward to meeting Heimin from all over the world!
会場にはおら行けねえよっていう人も全然大丈夫！
For those who can't make it to the venue, that's totally fine too!
配信チケットはSPWNとZAIKOで販売します。
Streaming tickets will be sold on SPWN and ZAIKO.
こちらも21時から販売開始なので
Sales for these also start at 9:00 PM...
配信でね、ぜひ僕の勇姿を見に来てください！
...so please come watch my performance on the stream!
各がくせ、じゃ間違えたわ。
Each stude... whoops, I messed up.
各座席のエリアマップはこちら！
Here is the seat map for each area!
S席は1階と3階前方、A席は1階後方と2階
S seats are on the 1st and 3rd floor front, A seats are on the 1st floor back and 2nd floor...
B席は3階後方と4階に分かれています。
...and B seats are on the 3rd floor back and 4th floor.
おれ、いっぱい、いっぱい来てね、散らばってくれ！
Please come in crowds and spread out!
そして皆様お待ちかねのグッズ情報もあります！
And there's also the merchandise info you've been waiting for!
グッズをね、このあと21時より販売開始してるので
Merchandise will be on sale starting from 9:00 PM...
まずはライブに欠かせない応援セットをご紹介！じゃじゃん！
...first, let me introduce the 'Support Set' which is essential for the live! Ta-da!
キチャ！うぱおライトは見たのとおり
Here it is! As you can see, the Upao Light...
うぱおがモチーフになりました。おまえらもずっと欲しいって言ってたもんね。
...is based on Upao. You guys kept saying you wanted one.
ライブ会場うぱおで埋め尽くしましょう！
Let's fill the concert venue with Upao!
Tシャツは今回のライブタイトルにある
The T-shirt has a crosshair mark motif...
LOCK ONにちなんで胸に照準マークをモチーフプリントしてみました。
...printed on the chest, inspired by the live title 'LOCK ON'.
みんなのね、あの心臓僕が思い切り撃ち抜いてあげますので
I'll shoot right through all your hearts...
ぜひ天界に遊びに来てください、ライブでもぜひ来てください！
...so please come visit the celestial realm, and please come to the live!
フェイスタオルはロゴを大きくあしらったデザインになっていて
The face towel has a design with a large logo...
これね、弾丸で撃ち抜かれたイメージでかっこいいので
...this too is cool with an image of being shot by bullets...
こちらもね、みんなTシャツと一緒に身につけてくれたら嬉しいなと思います。
...I'd be happy if everyone wore it along with the T-shirt.
セット特典のラバーバンドはクリア素材で涼しげなデザイン。
The set-exclusive rubber band has a refreshing design with clear material.
ロゴが入った特別仕様なのでみんなぜひゲットしてね！
It's a special version with the logo, so everyone, please get one!
内側に「COVER」って書いてありました。
It says 'COVER' on the inside.
それぞれのグッズは単品でも販売します！
Each item will also be sold individually!
他の先行グッズはこちら！じゃん！
Here are the other pre-sale items! Ta-da!
リングライトとはっぴも先行発送対象となります。
The ring light and happi coat are also available for pre-sale.
はっぴ欲しかったでしょう？
You wanted a happi coat, right?
リングライトにもね、「ここ撃ち抜いて」ってアピールできるように
On the ring light too, I put a crosshair icon...
照準アイコン入れてみました。
...so you can appeal with 'shoot here'.
平民のみんな僕がもうどんどん、どんどんおまえらを撃ち抜いていくので
Heimin everyone, I'll keep on shooting you all down...
ぜひライブで光らせてください！
...so please make them glow at the live!
はっぴは背面にキービジュアルのかなたそ大きくあしらいました。
The happi coat features a large illustration of Kanata-so from the key visual on the back.
ね、サイバーチックなデザインにもしてもらいましたが、
I also had it made with a cyber-tech design,
ソーラン節もちょっと浮かぶよね。
but it also kind of reminds me of Soran Bushi.
平民のみんな、
Heimin everyone,
おめーら当然フル装備で応援してくれかな！
make sure to support me in full gear!
リングライトとハッピは
Actually, the ring light and happi
応援セットには実は含まれませんので、
aren't included in the cheer set,
このへんね、あの、注意してください。
so please be careful about that.
そして、受注販売グッズはこちら！
And here are the made-to-order goods!
じゃじゃーん！
Ta-da!
これ、トートバッグがすごい良かった、サンプル見たんですけど。
The tote bag was really great, I saw the sample.
トートバッグはね、
The tote bag,
痛バッグとしても使えるように
can also be used as an 'ita-bag',
缶バッジ飾れる透明のポケットがついてて、
as it has a transparent pocket for badges,
キャリーケースのハンドルに通せる通し穴もあるので、
and it has a loop for a suitcase handle,
旅行の時も片手で持ち運べると。すごいです、これ。
so you can carry it one-handed. It's amazing.
で、モチーフキーホルダーが
The motif key holder is modeled after
キービジュアルの僕の首元にあるドッグタグというものをイメージしました。
the dog tag around my neck in the key visual.
かっこいいデザインなのでバッグやポーチにつけてみてください。
It's a cool design, so please put it on your bag.
アクリルスタンドも、これもね、さっき見た、すごかった。
The acrylic stand, too, was incredible.
背景の展開トラスとかなたそがね、別パーツになってるんで、
The background truss and Kanata-so are separate,
立体的に飾れてます。すごい立体感あった。もう4Dでしたね。
so it looks 3D. It had amazing depth. Like 4D.
そしてそして、最後に注意事項です。グッズの販売期間はこのあと、
And finally, some notes. The sales period is
21時から6月23日18時までです。
from 21:00 until 18:00 on June 23rd.
おんでみんな、ややこしいからね、あれなんだけど、注意してほしいのが、
And everyone, it's a bit complicated, but...
先行発送グッズはライブの前に届く予定なんですけど、
Pre-order goods arrive before the live concert,
受注販売グッズはライブ後、これあとなんですよ、
but made-to-order goods arrive after it.
受注販売グッズね。間違えないようにチェックしてください。
Please check so you don't get them mixed up.
ぜひ、よろしくお願いします。詳しい情報は公式サイト、
Please look forward to it. Check the official site,
公式X、販売サイト、そして、公式特設サイトをご確認ください。
official X, and the special site for more info.
告知は以上になります！
That's all for the announcements!
ということで、ソロライブはしくじらないように頑張りたいと思います。
I'll do my best not to screw up my solo live.
ね、ちょっと前にさ、エイプリルフールに双子の妹登場させたりしたじゃん。
A while ago on April Fools', I had my twin sister appear.
なんか、あいつすごい人気になっちゃったりとかしてさ、
She ended up becoming really popular, you know?
そういうね、ちょっと入れられてないしくじりとかも色々あるんですけど。
There are many screw-ups I couldn't include today.
ま、これからのホロライブ人生、
Well, in my future Hololive life,
しくじることは確実にあると思いますが、そんな天音かなたを、
I'm sure I'll screw up again, but please support me,
そして、初めてのソロライブを、よろしくお願いします。
and my first solo live. Thank you.
一緒にカートに入れたらアウト？わからない、
Is it bad to put them in the cart together?
あとでちょっと調べとくわ、みんな、また言うわ。
I'll look into it and tell you all later.
ありがとね。ややこしいぞ、わかる。
Thanks. It is confusing, I know.
ということで、それじゃあみんな、また、おつかなたー！
Well then, everyone, see you later, Otsukanata!
ありがとう！MVに飛んでくれ！
Thank you! Go watch the MV!
やー！
Yah!
バイバーイ！
Bye bye!